Guide to the Harper Leiper Studios Houston Aerial Photographs
University of Houston Libraries
Harper Leiper Studios Houston Aerial Photographs
1976-1982
2007-016
Harper Leiper Studios
0.50 Linear Feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
The Harper Leiper Studios Houston Aerial Photographs Collection contains aerial photographs of Houston during the 1970s and early 1980s taken by commercial photographers Harper Leiper Studios.
Historical Note:
The city began on August 30, 1836, when Augustus Chapman Allen and John Kirby Allen ran an advertisement in the Telegraph and Texas Register for the "Town of Houston." The town-site, which featured a mixture of timber and grassland, was on the level Coastal Plain in the middle of the future Harris County, at 95.4° west longitude and 30.3° north latitude. When first formed in 1949 the Houston Standard Metropolitan Statistical Area covered only Harris County and had a population of 806,701 people. The increasing use of automobiles also led to the building of expressways in the 1950s that extended over 200 miles by 1990. The prosperity after World War II brought the world famous Galleria shopping mall with its interior ice-skating rink in 1970. In the ordering of urban space Houston politicians and voters have continually rejected the use of zoning. The lack of zoning has not affected development to any great extent, however, since heavy industry concentrated in the area of the ship channel and subdivisions controlled construction through deed restrictions. This casual attitude toward land use encouraged business expansion.
Sources:
Handbook of Texas Online, s.v. "Houston, Texas." http://www.tshaonline.org/handbook/online/articles/HH/hdh3.html Accessed March 5, 2009
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Genre/Form of Material:
Photographs
Geographic Name:
Houston (Tex.) -- History; Houston (Tex.) -- Pictorial works
Acquisition Information:
John Gilderbloom, University of Louisville
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Harper Leiper Studios Houston Aerial Photographs Collection contains aerial photographs of Houston during the 1970s and early 1980s taken by commercial photographers Harper Leiper Studios.
Detailed List of Contents
- Westheimer-East, September 1976 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Downtown Houston, September 1976 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Bellaire, October 1976 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Downtown Houston, November, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Sharpstown, May 1976 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Hempstead, April 1979 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Downtown, November 1979 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Westheimer-East, May 1980 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- [Westheimer-East], May 1981 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  (4 copies)
- Untitled, October, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Untitled, March 1982 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Bellaire, September 1982 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Bellaire, October 1982 (Box 1, Folder 13)